Educational Technology Services Records UA245
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Great Courses, 2014 -- 2017; UA245.001; 626 Digital Object(s); 1 Web sites
  - Philosophy 167: Class 7 - Part 11 - The State of Galileo's Science of Local Motion: Eight Principles, and Questions Raised., 2014-10-14; gc.phil167.86
    Synopsis: Explains Galileo's eight principles of motion, and the resulting questions which are considered by subsequent scientists. Opening line: "Galileo is gonna leave the world with eight principles." Duration: 6:44 minutes. Segment: Class 7, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 7 - Part 12 - Getting Beyond Mere Conjecture: What Galileo Achieved, and the Problem of Scientific Truth., 2014-10-14; gc.phil167.87
    Synopsis: Discusses Galileo's views on the relationship between theory, experimental results, and scientific truth, and the nature of science. Opening line: "Okay. This is from a note that Galileo published concerning the supernova of 1604." Duration: 10:45 minutes. Segment: Class 7, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 1 - Three Post-Copernican Generations- the Key Figures, and the Empirical Limitations of the Theorizing., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.613
    Synopsis: Introduces several key figures, including, Ren Descartes, Marin Mersenne, and Pierre Gassendi; notes that there are limits to theorizing. Opening line: "So tonight we start what I like to call the third post-Copernican generation when turning to Descartes." Duration: 10:26 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 2 - Ren Descartes- Biography., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.614
    Synopsis: A brief biography of Ren Descartes Opening line: "All right, this is a chronological table from what surely is the best biography, intellectual biography in English." Duration: 13:21 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 3 - Discourse on Method- Descartes' Theory of Lenses, and the Reduction of Symbolic Methods to Geometry., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.615
    Synopsis: Overview of Descartes' Discourse on Method; emphasizing optics, refraction, and geometry. Opening line: "Discourse on the method of rightly conducting one's reason, and seeking the truth in the sciences, and in addition, the optics, the meteorology, and the geometry, which are essays in this method." Duration: 16:02 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 4 - The Significance of Descartes' Principia- Its Influence, and the Reconceptualization of Curvilinear Motion., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.616
    Synopsis: Overview of Descartes' Principia Philosophiae and Descartes' reconceptualization of curvilinear motion. Opening line: "All right, so the Principia, let's spend the rest of our time on Descartes save for one letter he wrote, that we'll look at next week." Duration: 11:21 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 5 - The Mechanical Philosophy- the "Contact" Constraint on Theorizing, and Vacuums., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.617
    Synopsis: Overview of mechanical philosophy, the principle of contact and the concept of vacuums Opening line: "And some people, maybe it's in the need to write a new dissertation and say something that hasn't been said before. Are trying to get away from the idea that the principle feature or the mechanical philosophy was contact." Duration: 10:34 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 6 - Descartes' Response to Pyrrhonism- A Unified, Foundationally Secure, Fully Comprehensive Science., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.618
    Synopsis: Descartes' response to Pyrrhonism; an introduction to Girard Desargues. Opening line: "Now the big thing here, and I mentioned this before, how is Descartes working with a mechanical philosophy gonna safeguard against error?" Duration: 3:08 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 7 - Two Hard Cases for Mechanical Philosophy- Descartes' Accounts of Magnetism and Gravity., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.619
    Synopsis: Review of Descartes' accounts for magnetism and gravity. Opening line: "Obviously, a terrible difficulty facing the mechanical philosophy was magnetism." Duration: 7:20 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 9 - The First Two Laws of Natural Motion- the Principle of Inertia, and the Sling Argument., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.620
    Synopsis: Defines Descartes' understanding of a law, reviews the principle of inertia and the sling argument. Opening line: "Now we get to the laws, and what in the world does the term law mean?" Duration: 8:55 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 10 - Gassendi and Inertia- the Importance of the Principle in the Context of Celestial Motion, and the Conceptual Change it Represents., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.621
    Synopsis: Continues with inertia; re-introduces Gassendi. Opening line: "Now, these two laws together, the first and second law, appear to be stating what we now call the principle of inertia." Duration: 8:34 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 11 - The Third Law of Natural Motion- Descartes' Account of Impact., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.622
    Synopsis: Descartes' third law of natural motion--the issue of impact. Opening line: "The third law of motion. This is very different." Duration: 8:15 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 12 - Rules of Motion- a Theory of Colliding Spheres, and Its Justification., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.623
    Synopsis: Reviews a chart of seven cases created by Eric Aiton and discusses a theory of colliding spheres. Opening line: "So the rules, he proceeds to give in this way you saw them written out." Duration: 7:05 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 13 - Defending the Rules- Spinoza's Defense, and Descartes' Emphasis on Reason Over Experience., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.624
    Synopsis: Briefly talks about Spinoza's defense; discusses that experience often seems to contradict the rules. Opening line: "Spinoza tries to do his best with these rules." Duration: 3:46 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 8 - Part 14 - Relativity of Motion- Descartes' View in the Principia, and His View in Le Monde., 2014-10-21; gc.phil167.625
    Synopsis: Descartes' views on motion. Opening line: "Descartes says in parts of, sections of part two, that I'm reserving more for next week, that geometrically all motion is relative." Duration: 12:43 minutes. Segment: Class 8, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 1 - Descartes on Galileo: the Lack of Foundations for the Theory in Two New Sciences., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.88
    Synopsis: Discusses Descartes' belief that Galileo did not properly establish the foundations for his theory of projectile motion. Opening line: "All right, let me dig in. I'm gonna start with the Descartes letter to Mersenne on Galileo." Duration: 17:32 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 2 - Descartes' Vortex Theory: Three Kinds of Matter, Vortices, and the Creation and Capture of Planets., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.89
    Synopsis: Outlines Descartes' model of planetary motions as a vortex centered on the Sun, with three kinds of matter for stars, planets, and the space between them. Opening line: "It's worth reading the whole thing. This is the lead in as you see it's way up at article number 30 and part 3. But it's the lead in to the vortex theory." Duration: 13:49 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 3 - Vortices inside of Vortices: Descartes' Theory of Planetary Vortices, and of the Vortices of the Moons., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.90
    Synopsis: Descartes suggests that vortices within vortices explains how the Galilean satellites go around Jupiter and the Moon goes around the Earth, while the planets go around the Sun. Opening line: "Now, he's right about that. There are vortices inside of vortices." Duration: 11:38 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 4 - A Hypothetico-Explanatory Approach to Theorizing: Descartes' Method of Constructing Theoretically and Empirically Sound Explanations., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.91
    Synopsis: Descartes keeps his theories firmly linked to the observable, empirical effects, unlike Galileo. Opening line: "There's an approach to theorizing here that's probably worth looking at, and it's my summary of it." Duration: 3:37 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 5 - Celestial Motion in Vortices: Descartes' Copernicanism, and His Definition of Movement., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.92
    Synopsis: Descartes supported a Copernican model over Tychonian, and defined movement as a relative motion rather than absolute. Opening line: "All right, his Copernicanism is fairly easy to explain, that these are his diagrams." Duration: 7:32 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 6 - Quantifying the Tendency to Recede: the Sling Argument, and the Force Displayed by the Tension in the Sling., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.93
    Synopsis: Discusses centripetal force and tension in Descartes' vortices, using his diagrams of a spinning sling. Opening line: "Next thing I'm gonna do, there's a passage that starts with article 56 and I'm giving it to you. There are five pages in Latin." Duration: 12:29 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 7 - The Parochiality of Celestial Motion: Descartes' Physics and the Total Variability of Orbital Movement., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.94
    Synopsis: Descartes believed, correctly, that the orbits of the planets are constantly changing, affected by one another, which undercuts the idea that underlying physics can be determined from observation. Opening line: "This is now a totally different thing, but it's fairly important. I changed this slide today because it originally just had the top and the bottom." Duration: 7:36 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 8 - The New Astronomical Physics: Descartes' View, and Six Questions Raised by His Physics., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.95
    Synopsis: Descartes posed six questions to be answered by astronomy. Opening line: "All right, so we end up with two views of astronomy coming out of this. The Keplerian view we've inherited to develop a mathematical account of the motions that yields calculated longitudes and latitudes that at all times." Duration: 3:59 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 9 - Terrestrial Consequences of Celestial Vortices: Descartes' Theory of the Tides., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.96
    Synopsis: Describes how Descartes applied his vortex theory to explain tides,. Opening line: "At any rate, the questions are important. I wanna do two last things and then take a break." Duration: 7:54 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 10 - The Conclusion of the Principia: Five Principles that Establish the Absolute Certainty of Descartes' Physics., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.97
    Synopsis: The conclusion of Descartes' Principia argues that his methods prove his theory. Opening line: "All right what I'm going to end with from the book. And it's gonna be a discussion of Descartes science but picked up initially from what Descartes himself says" Duration: 13:40 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 11 - The Science of Descartes' Principia: a New Way of Turning Data Into Evidence, and Its Shortcomings., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.98
    Synopsis: Descartes approached science empirically, but did not use it to predict new things which could be tested experimentally. Opening line: "Drake said that Descartes's whole Principia is unscientific and we read it and it seems so far removed from our science that you can legitimately ask, 'Why do we even take this to be science at all.?'. " Duration: 7:41 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 12 - A Modern Example of a Similar Science: Darwin's Theory of Heredity and Evolution., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.99
    Synopsis: Darwin's approach to the Theory of Evolution was in some ways similar to Descartes' emprical science. Opening line: "Now I forewarned Patrick of this so he can also just say, I don't want to talk about this." Duration: 8:21 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 13 - Descartes' Contributions to Mechanics and Astronomy: Questions Raised, and the Aims of Empirical Research., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.100
    Synopsis: Summarizes the contributions of Descartes to mechanics and astronomy. Opening line: "Contributions to mechanics. There are some really important ones by Descartes." Duration: 11:59 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 9 - Part 14 - The Rise of Modern Science: the Empirical World as the Ultimate Arbiter for Answering Questions About It., 2014-10-28; gc.phil167.101
    Synopsis: After 1650, more scientists take as a given that theory must be based on empirical observation. Opening line: "Something very curious happens at this point in time. And it'll show up in this course because almost everything we read from now on in the last five weeks of this course and throughout almost all the second semester, is going to look like modern science to an extent, nothing we've read so far." Duration: 16:00 minutes. Segment: Class 9, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 1 - Review of Several Major Figures: Christiaan Huygens, Isaac Newton, and a Brief Biography of Constantine Huygens., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.102
    Synopsis: Continues with the theme of mechanics and introduces Christiaan Huygens and Isaac Newton and a brief biography of Constantijn Huygens. Opening line: "Next three classes, which means, not next Tuesday. So this is spread over four weeks, but three classes. They're all gonna look at the period, primarily 1650 to 1680." Duration: 8:22 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 2 - Christiaan Huygens: a Biography., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.103
    Synopsis: Brief biography of Christiaan Huygens. Opening line: "All right, now Christiaan, the second child. The first thing we really know of him is in the mid 1640s, 1645, 46." Duration: 18:21 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 3 - Huygens' Mechanics: Cycloidal Pendulums, and the Invention of an Extremely Precise Clock., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.104
    Synopsis: Chiefly reviews Huygens' invention of an extremely accurate clock. Opening line: "He, because of Alexandre Courrier writing on Descartes and Newton, he portrayed Huygens as a Cartesian." Duration: 8:47 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 4 - Surface Gravity: Two Theory-Mediated Measurements, Via Conical and Cycloidal Pendulums., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.105
    Synopsis: Huygens' attempts at measuring the strength of surface gravity. Opening line: "As I said, in October of 1659, he got compulsively preoccupied with measuring the strength of surface gravity." Duration: 7:30 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 5 - Extensive Measurements of Surface Gravity: Huygens' Method., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.106
    Synopsis: Continues with Huygens' attempts at measuring the strength of surface gravity. Opening line: "These are his instructions. You'll see the date, 1686. 1686 is when Newton is busily finishing the Principia, unbeknownst to Huygens, he's busily finishing this." Duration: 7:49 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 6 - Impact of Hard (Elastic) Spheres: Huygens' Solution, and Several Significant Consequences of It., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.107
    Synopsis: Briefly introduces Christopher Wren and John Wallis; discusses impact of spheres and Huygens' solution. Opening line: "Impact. We of course know Descartes' impact." Duration: 6:34 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 7 - Impact of Hard Spheres: Newton's Algebraic Solution, and Huygens' Relativity Principle., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.108
    Synopsis: Reviews Newton's algebraic solution to the question of impact of hard spheres. Opening line: "Newton has a series of lectures on algebra teaching his students." Duration: 5:53 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 8 - Huygens' Theory of Impact: Against Descartes' Theory, a General Solution, and an Empirically Testable, Striking Result., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.109
    Synopsis: Continues discussing Huygen's development of a theory of impact. Opening line: "So whats he do now. Now I am gonna turn to the publication you've seen. The publication I assigned." Duration: 13:34 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 9 - Huygens' Theory of Centrifugal Force: Solving for the Tension in a String., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.110
    Synopsis: Reviews Huygen's paper De Vi Centrifuga, which were put as an appendix to Horologium Oscillatorium. Opening line: "All right, next topic is De Vi Centrifuga, this paper which, again, appeared in 1703." Duration: 9:28 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 9.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 10 - Tests of Huygen's Theory of Centrifugal Force: Conical Pendulums, Circular Arc Pendulums, and Paraboloids., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.111
    Synopsis: Describes how Huygen tests his theory and the three results. Opening line: "How's he test this theory? Well, there are three results." Duration: 3:40 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 10.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 11 - Converging Theory-Mediated Measurements of Surface Gravity: Using Cycloidal and Conical Pendulums to Confirm Different Principles of Motion., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.112
    Synopsis: Describes Huygen using cycloidal and conical pendulums to confirm different principles of motion. Opening line: "All right. I said earlier that Huygens had measured, in 1659, measured surface gravity with a constant height conical pendulum." Duration: 12:04 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 11.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 12 - Horologium Oscillatorium: Hypotheses, and Select Propositions from Parts I-III., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.113
    Synopsis: Begins an overview of the Horologium Oscillatorium. Opening line: "Different subject. Now I'm gonna just take you through Horologium Oscillatorium for a couple of minutes." Duration: 12:40 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 12.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 13 - Horologium Oscillatorium: the Center of Oscillation Problem, and Using Deviations from Idealized Theory to Refine the Theorizing., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.114
    Synopsis: Continues with an overview of the Horologium Oscillatorium. Opening line: "Now part four of the Horologium Oscillatorium, the last difficult part of the thing." Duration: 12:41 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 13.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 14 - Horologium Oscillatorium: the Center of Oscillation for Cycloidal Pendulums., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.115
    Synopsis: Concludes with an overview of the Horologium Oscillatorium. Opening line: "hese are two of the last three paragraphs of part four." Duration: 4:16 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 14.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 10 - Part 15 - Huygens' Accomplishments: Questions Answered, and the Birth of Theoretical Physics., 2014-11-04; gc.phil167.116
    Synopsis: Reviews Huygens' influence on later scientists. Opening line: "I want to accomplish just as now summarizing on the night." Duration: 12:02 minutes. Segment: Class 10, Part 15.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 1 - Astronomy, Mechanics, and Mathematics in the Mid 1600s: a Review of Major Figures., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.117
    Synopsis: This begins an overview of important scientists and developments between Descartes and Newton. Opening line: "So look, what we're doing, what we're in the middle of is three classes interrupted by a holiday on November 11th, three classes looking at the period from the early 1640s." Duration: 10:44 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 1.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 2 - Alternatives to the Area Rule: Ismal Bullialdus, Vincent Wing, and Three New Methods for Calculating Orbits., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.118
    Synopsis: Ismael Boulliau and Vincent Wing developed alternatives to Keplers Laws. Opening line: "All right. The first person to come along and offer a full system alternative to Kepler's was Ismael Boulleau." Duration: 9:45 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 2.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 3 - New Technology: Huygens' Clocks, Telescopes, and the Discovery of Titan and Saturn's Ring., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.119
    Synopsis: Christian and Constantine Huygens developed very accurate astronomical clocks and telescopes. Christian discovered Titan, the largest satellite of Saturn, and identified a previously mysterious feature as a ring around Saturn. Opening line: "There were major advances in observational astronomy during this time." Duration: 8:32 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 3.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 4 - Observational Astronomy in Bologna: Cassini's Observations at San Petronio., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.120
    Synopsis: Cassini executed high-precision observations of the sun and planets, producing very accurate measurements of their motions and features. Opening line: "The next few slides are going to be focused on Bologna and I will confess to everybody there is nothing I am more vain about. Than my own photographs." Duration: 11:29 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 4.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 5 - Thomas Streete: Astronomia Carolina, Tables, and Another New Method for Calculating Orbits., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.121
    Synopsis: Thomas Street published Astronomia Carolina, in which he promoted proposals and observations originally made by Horrocks. Opening line: "1661 is the publication of Thomas Street's Astronomia Carolina." Duration: 10:14 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 5.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 6 - Nicholas Mercator: Another New Method for Calculating Orbits., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.122
    Synopsis: Mercator published his own alternative to the area rule for orbits. Opening line: "Just continuing for a moment now, this is jumping ahead to 1676." Duration: 10:13 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 6.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 7 - The Founding of the Royal Society: the Fellows, and Philosophical Transactions., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.123
    Synopsis: The Royal Society of London was founded in 1663, and included many of the great scientists of the time. The Philosophical Transactions became an important mechanism for scientific communication. Opening line: "I spoke before magnetical philosophy. What I'm gonna shift on to for the next few minutes is England right after Street, before and after Street." Duration: 16:27 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 7.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 8 - Hooke's Micrographia: Microscopic Observations of Small Entities, and a Brief Biography., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.124
    Synopsis: Robert Hooke made important discoveries with a microscope. Opening line: "So picture yourself in France now. They've got this society forming, and they have their own journal, etcetra." Duration: 4:59 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 8.
  - Philosophy 167: Class 11 - Part 9 - The Founding of the Royal Academy: the Scholars, the Royal Observatory, and Cassini's Observations of Saturn., 2014-11-18; gc.phil167.125
    Synopsis: The Royal Academy of Sciences was founded in 1666, with Cassini the first royal astronomer of France. Opening line: "All right, so England is in the process of forming the royal society, with Marx' success." Duration: 7:43 minutes. Segment: Class 11, Part 9.